and there I was after five years fighting against Parliament in front of three of Britain's most eminent High Court judges waiting for their ruling about whether or not Parliament had to release this data. And I've got to tell you, I wasn't that hopeful, because I'd seen the establishment. I thought, it always sticks together. I am out of luck. Well, guess what? I won. Hooray. (Applause) Well, that's not exactly the story, because the problem was that Parliament delayed and delayed releasing that data, and then they tried to retrospectively change the law so that it would no longer apply to them. The transparency law they'd passed earlier that applied to everybody else, they tried to keep it so it didn't apply to them. What they hadn't counted on was digitization, because that meant that all those paper receipts had been scanned in electronically, and it was very easy for somebody to just copy that entire database, put it on a disk, and then just saunter outside of Parliament, which they did, and then they shopped that disk to the highest bidder, which was the Daily Telegraph, and then, you all remember, there was weeks and weeks of revelations, everything from porn movies and bath plugs and new kitchens and mortgages that had never been paid off. The end result was six ministers resigned, the first speaker of the house in 300 years was forced to resign, a new government was elected on a mandate of transparency, 120 MPs stepped down at that election, and so far, four MPs and two lords have done jail time for fraud. So, thank you. (Applause) Well, I tell you that story because it wasn't unique to Britain. It was an example of a culture clash that's happening all over the world between bewigged and bestockinged officials who think that they can rule over us without very much prying from the public, and then suddenly confronted with a public who is no longer content with that arrangement, and not only not content with it, now, more often, armed with official data itself. So we are moving to this democratization of information, and I've been in this field for quite a while. Slightly embarrassing admission: Even when I was a kid, I used to have these little spy books, and I would, like, see what everybody was doing in my neighborhood and log it down. I think that was a pretty good indication about my future career as an investigative journalist, and what I've seen from being in this access to information field for so long is that it used to be quite a niche interest, and it's gone mainstream. Everybody, increasingly, around the world, wants to know about what people in power are doing. They want a say in decisions that are made in their name and with their money. It's this democratization of information that I think is an information enlightenment, and it has many of the same principles of the first Enlightenment. It's about searching for the truth, not because somebody says it's true, "because I say so." No, it's about trying to find the truth based on what you can see and what can be tested. That, in the first Enlightenment, led to questions about the right of kings, the divine right of kings to rule over people, or that women should be subordinate to men, or that the Church was the official word of God. Obviously the Church weren't very happy about this, and they tried to suppress it, but what they hadn't counted on was technology, and then they had the printing press, which suddenly enabled these ideas to spread cheaply, far and fast, and people would come together in coffee houses, discuss the ideas, plot revolution. In our day, we have digitization. That strips all the physical mass out of information, so now it's almost zero cost to copy and share information. Our printing press is the Internet. Our coffee houses are social networks. We're moving to what I would think of as a fully connected system, and we have global decisions to make in this system, decisions about climate, about finance systems, about resources. And think about it -- if we want to make an important decision about buying a house, we don't just go off. I mean, I don't know about you, but I want to see a lot of houses before I put that much money into it. And if we're thinking about a finance system, we need a lot of information to take in. It's just not possible for one person to take in the amount, the volume of information, and analyze it to make good decisions. So that's why we're seeing increasingly this demand for access to information. That's why we're starting to see more disclosure laws come out, so for example, on the environment, there's the Aarhus Convention, which is a European directive that gives people a very strong right to know, so if your water company is dumping water into your river, sewage water into your river, you have a right to know about it. In the finance industry, you now have more of a right to know about what's going on, so we have different anti-bribery laws, money regulations, increased corporate disclosure, so you can now track assets across borders. And it's getting harder to hide assets, tax avoidance, pay inequality. So that's great. We're starting to find out more and more about these systems. And they're all moving to this central system, this fully connected system, all of them except one. Can you guess which one? It's the system which underpins all these other systems. It's the system by which we organize and exercise power, and there I'm talking about politics, because in politics, we're back to this system, this top-down hierarchy. And how is it possible that the volume of information can be processed that needs to in this system? Well, it just can't. That's it. And I think this is largely what's behind the crisis of legitimacy in our different governments right now. So I've told you a bit about what I did to try and drag Parliament, kicking and screaming, into the 21st century, and I'm just going to give you a couple of examples of what a few other people I know are doing. So this is a guy called Seb Bacon. He's a computer programmer, and he built a site called Alaveteli, and what it is, it's a Freedom of Information platform. It's open-source, with documentation, and it allows you to make a Freedom of Information request, to ask your public body a question, so it takes all the hassle out of it, and I can tell you that there is a lot of hassle making these requests, so it takes all of that hassle out, and you just type in your question, for example, how many police officers have a criminal record? It zooms it off to the appropriate person, it tells you when the time limit is coming to an end, it keeps track of all the correspondence, it posts it up there, and it becomes an archive of public knowledge. So that's open-source and it can be used in any country where there is some kind of Freedom of Information law. So there's a list there of the different countries that have it, and then there's a few more coming on board. So if any of you out there like the sound of that and have a law like that in your country, I know that Seb would love to hear from you about collaborating and getting that into your country. This is Birgitta Jónsdóttir. She's an Icelandic MP. And quite an unusual MP. In Iceland, she was one of the protesters who was outside of Parliament when the country's economy collapsed, and then she was elected on a reform mandate, and she's now spearheading this project. It's the Icelandic Modern Media Initiative, and they've just got funding to make it an international modern media project, and this is taking all of the best laws around the world about freedom of expression, protection of whistleblowers, protection from libel, source protection, and trying to make Iceland a publishing haven. It's a place where your data can be free, so when we think about, increasingly, how governments want to access user data, what they're trying to do in Iceland is make this safe haven where it can happen. In my own field of investigative journalism, we're also having to start thinking globally, so this is a site called Investigative Dashboard. And if you're trying to track a dictator's assets, for example, Hosni Mubarak, you know, he's just funneling out cash from his country when he knows he's in trouble, and what you want to do to investigate that is, you need to have access to all of the world's, as many as you can, companies' house registrations databases. So this is a website that tries to agglomerate all of those databases into one place so you can start searching for, you know, his relatives, his friends, the head of his security services. You can try and find out how he's moving out assets from that country. But again, when it comes to the decisions which are impacting us the most, perhaps, the most important decisions that are being made about war and so forth, again we can't just make a Freedom of Information request. It's really difficult. So we're still having to rely on illegitimate ways of getting information, through leaks. So when the Guardian did this investigation about the Afghan War, you know, they can't walk into the Department of Defense and ask for all the information. You know, they're just not going to get it. So this came from leaks of tens of thousands of dispatches that were written by American soldiers about the Afghan War, and leaked, and then they're able to do this investigation. Another rather large investigation is around world diplomacy. Again, this is all based around leaks, 251,000 U.S. diplomatic cables, and I was involved in this investigation because I got this leak through a leak from a disgruntled WikiLeaker and ended up going to work at the Guardian. So I can tell you firsthand what it was like to have access to this leak. It was amazing. I mean, it was amazing. It reminded me of that scene in "The Wizard of Oz." Do you know the one I mean? Where the little dog Toto runs across to where the wizard [is], and he pulls back, the dog's pulling back the curtain, and -- "Don't look behind the screen. Don't look at the man behind the screen." It was just like that, because what you started to see is that all of these grand statesmen, these very pompous politicians, they were just like us. They all bitched about each other. I mean, quite gossipy, those cables. Okay, but I thought it was a very important point for all of us to grasp, these are human beings just like us. They don't have special powers. They're not magic. They are not our parents. Beyond that, what I found most fascinating was the level of endemic corruption that I saw across all different countries, and particularly centered around the heart of power, around public officials who were embezzling the public's money for their own personal enrichment, and allowed to do that because of official secrecy. So I've mentioned WikiLeaks, because surely what could be more open than publishing all the material? Because that is what Julian Assange did. He wasn't content with the way the newspapers published it to be safe and legal. He threw it all out there. That did end up with vulnerable people in Afghanistan being exposed. It also meant that the Belarussian dictator was given a handy list of all the pro-democracy campaigners in that country who had spoken to the U.S. government. Is that radical openness? I say it's not, because for me, what it means, it doesn't mean abdicating power, responsibility, accountability, it's actually being a partner with power. It's about sharing responsibility, sharing accountability. Also, the fact that he threatened to sue me because I got a leak of his leaks, I thought that showed a remarkable sort of inconsistency in ideology, to be honest, as well. (Laughs) The other thing is that power is incredibly seductive, and you must have two real qualities, I think, when you come to the table, when you're dealing with power, talking about power, because of its seductive capacity. You've got to have skepticism and humility. Skepticism, because you must always be challenging. I want to see why do you -- you just say so? That's not good enough. I want to see the evidence behind why that's so. And humility because we are all human. We all make mistakes. And if you don't have skepticism and humility, then it's a really short journey to go from reformer to autocrat, and I think you only have to read "Animal Farm" to get that message about how power corrupts people. So what is the solution? It is, I believe, to embody within the rule of law rights to information. At the moment our rights are incredibly weak. In a lot of countries, we have Official Secrets Acts, including in Britain here. We have an Official Secrets Act with no public interest test. So that means it's a crime, people are punished, quite severely in a lot of cases, for publishing or giving away official information. Now wouldn't it be amazing, and really, this is what I want all of you to think about, if we had an Official Disclosure Act where officials were punished if they were found to have suppressed or hidden information that was in the public interest? So that -- yes. Yes! My power pose. (Applause) (Laughs) I would like us to work towards that. So it's not all bad news. I mean, there definitely is progress on the line, but I think what we find is that the closer that we get right into the heart of power, the more opaque, closed it becomes. So it was only just the other week that I heard London's Metropolitan Police Commissioner talking about why the police need access to all of our communications, spying on us without any judicial oversight, and he said it was a matter of life and death. He actually said that, it was a matter of life and death. There was no evidence. He presented no evidence of that. It was just, "Because I say so. You have to trust me. Take it on faith." Well, I'm sorry, people, but we are back to the pre-Enlightenment Church, and we need to fight against that. So he was talking about the law in Britain which is the Communications Data Bill, an absolutely outrageous piece of legislation. In America, you have the Cyber Intelligence Sharing and Protection Act. You've got drones now being considered for domestic surveillance. You have the National Security Agency building the world's giantest spy center. It's just this colossal -- it's five times bigger than the U.S. Capitol, in which they're going to intercept and analyze communications, traffic and personal data to try and figure out who's the troublemaker in society. Well, to go back to our original story, the parents have panicked. They've locked all the doors. They've kitted out the house with CCTV cameras. They're watching all of us. They've dug a basement, and they've built a spy center to try and run algorithms and figure out which ones of us are troublesome, and if any of us complain about that, we're arrested for terrorism. Well, is that a fairy tale or a living nightmare? Some fairy tales have happy endings. Some don't. I think we've all read the Grimms' fairy tales, which are, indeed, very grim. But the world isn't a fairy tale, and it could be more brutal than we want to acknowledge. Equally, it could be better than we've been led to believe, but either way, we have to start seeing it exactly as it is, with all of its problems, because it's only by seeing it with all of its problems that we'll be able to fix them and live in a world in which we can all be happily ever after. (Laughs) Thank you very much. (Applause) Thank you. (Applause)
et je me suis retrouvée, après ces cinq années de bataille contre le Parlement, face à trois des plus éminents juges de la Haute Cour britannique à attendre leur jugement concernant la communication de ces informations par le Parlement. Et je peux vous dire que je n'étais pas très optimiste car je connais les autorités. Je pensais "Elles sont toujours de mèche". Je n'ai pas de chance. Et bien, devinez quoi ? J'ai gagné. Hourra. (Applaudissements) Ce n'était pas aussi simple, le problème venait du Parlement qui ne cessait de retarder la divulgation des informations, et ensuite ils ont essayé de modifier la loi, rétroctivement, pour ne plus y être assujetti. La loi sur la transparence qu'ils avaient fait passé et qui s'appliquait à tous, ils ont tenté de faire en sorte qu'elle ne s'applique pas à eux. Mais ils n'avaient pas pensé à la numérisation, ce qui voulait dire que tous les reçus papier avaient été scannés, et il était donc facile de faire une copie de la base de donnée, de la mettre sur un CD et de sortir tranquillement du Parlement, et quelqu'un l'a fait, puis le CD a été vendu au plus offrant, en l'occurence Le Daily Telegraph. Puis, vous vous en souvenez tous, les révélations ont duré des semaines, du film porno au bouchon de baignoire, en passant par les prêts non remboursés et l'aménagement intérieur. En conséquence, six ministres ont démissionnés, pour la première fois en 300 ans, le président de l'assemblée a été contraint de démissionner, un nouveau gouvernement a été élu sous mandat de transparence, 120 parlementaires se sont retirés des élections, et à ce jour, quatre parlementaires et deux Lords ont été emprisonnés pour fraude. Merci. (Applaudissement) Je vous raconte cette histoire car elle ne se limite pas à la Grande-Bretagne. C'est un exemple du choc des cultures qui se produit partout dans le monde, entre officiels poudrés et emperruqués qui imaginent pouvoir gouverner sans curiosité de la part du public, et qui sont soudain confrontés à un public qui non seulement ne se satisfait plus de cet arrangement mais qui, désormais, est souvent armé de données officielles. Nous avançons vers la démocratisation de l'information, et je suis dans ce domaine depuis quelques temps maintenant. Confession légèrement embarrassante: Déjà, enfant, j'avais des petits livres d'espionnage et je regardais ce que faisaient les voisins et je le notais. Je pense que c'était un bon indice sur ma carrière de journaliste d'investigation, et ce que j'ai constaté depuis que je suis dans ce domaine de l'accès à l'information, c'est que c'était un centre d'intérêt assez fermé, et que ça s'est généralisé. De plus en plus de gens à travers le monde veulent savoir ce que font les dirigeants. Ils veulent avoir leur mot à dire concernant les décisions prises en leur nom, avec leur argent. Je pense que la démocratisation de l'information est un enseignement qui repose sur les même principes que l'enseignement des Lumières. Il s'agit de rechercher la vérité, et non pas parce que quelqu'un dit que c'est vrai, "parce que je le dis" Il s'agit d'essayer de découvrir la vérité d'après ce que l'on peut voir et ce qui peut être examiné. A l'époque des Lumières, cela a amené à s'interroger sur le Droit de Roi, le droit divin des monarques à diriger le peuple, sur la subordination des femmes aux hommes, sur l'Eglise comme parole officielle de Dieu. Evidemment, cela n'a pas trop plu à l'Eglise et ils ont essayé de le réprimer, mais ils n'avaient pas prévu l'arrivée de la technologie. L'imprimerie a soudain permis de diffuser ces idées, vite et loin, à moindre frais et les gens ont commencé à se retrouver dans des cafés, à discuter ces idées et à comploter la révolution. De nos jours, nous avons la numérisation, qui ôte toute masse physique à l'information, et c'est quasiment gratuit de copier et de partager cette information. Notre imprimerie, c'est Internet. Nos cafés, se sont les réseaux sociaux. Nous allons vers ce que j'appellerais un système entièrement connecté, et nous devons prendre des décisions globales à l'intérieur de ce système, des décisions concernant le climat, les systèmes financiers, les ressources. Et imaginez - si on a une décision importante à prendre concernant l'achat d'une maison, on ne se lance pas comme ça. Enfin, je ne sais pas pour vous, mais moi je veux voir plusieurs maisons avant d'y investir autant d'argent. Et pour le système financier, nous avons besoin de réunir beaucoup d'information. Et ce n'est tout simplement pas possible pour une seule personne de retenir un tel volume d'information, et de l'analyser pour prendre la bonne décision. C'est pour cela que nous voyons une demande croissante d'accès à l'information. C'est pour cela que nous pouvons voir de plus en plus de lois de divulgations. Par exemple, pour l'environnement il y a la Convention d'Aarhus, directive européene qui donne aux gens le droit d'être informé, donc si votre compagnie des eaux rejette des eaux dans votre rivière, des eaux usées, vous avez le droit de le savoir. Dans l'industrie de la finance, vous avez désormais plus de droits à être tenus informés, il y a par exemple les différentes loi anti-corruption, les règlementations sur l'argent, plus de transparence sur les entreprises, on peut localiser les actifs par-delà les frontières. Il devient de plus en plus difficile de dissimuler des avoirs, d'éviter de payer des impôts, les inégalités de rémunération. Donc ça c'est super. Nous commençons à en savoir de plus en plus sur ces systèmes. Et il s'orientent tous vers un système centralisé, ce système entièrement connecté, tous sauf un. Devinez lequel. C'est le système sur lequel tous les autres s'appuient; C'est le système par lequel nous organisons et exercons le pouvoir, et là je parle de politique, car en matière de politique, nous retournons à ce système, cette hiérarchie verticale. Comment peut-on traiter le volume nécessaire d'information dans ce système? Et bien, ce n'est pas possible. Tout simplement. Et je pense que c'est cela qui est, en grande partie, à l'origine de la crise de légitimité de nos différents gouvernements actuellement. Je vous ai en partie raconté ce que j'avais fait pour tenter d'amener le Parlement, à son corps défendant, dans le 21ème siècle, et je vais vous donner des exemples de ce que d'autres personnes sont en train de faire. Alors, il y a Seb Bacon. Il est programmeur informatique et il a crée le site Alaveteli, c'est une plateforme d'accès à l'information. Elle est libre d'accès, avec de la documentation, et elle vous permet de faire des requêtes d'accès à l'information, de poser une question à un organisme public, en vous facilitant la tâche, et je peux vous dire que c'est très compliqué de faire une requête, donc ça vous facilite la tâche, vous n'avez plus qu'à entrer votre question, par exemple, combien de policiers ont un casier judiciaire? C'est envoyé à la personne concernée, vous êtes informé lorsque le temps de délai arrive à expiration, l'historique des échanges est sauvegardé, c'est affiché et cela devient une archive publique. C'est ça l'accès libre, ou open-source, et ça peut être utilisé dans n'importe quel pays où il y a des lois de droit d'accès à l'information. Voici donc une liste des pays concernés, et d'autres y viennent. Alors si certains d'entre vous sont interéssés, et que vous avez une telle loi dans votre pays, je sais que Seb serait ravi de vous connaître afin de collaborer pour développer ça dans votre pays. Voici Birgitta Jónsdóttir, député islandaise plutôt insolite. En Islande, elle a participé à à la manifestation devant le Parlement lorsque l'économie du pays s'est effondrée, puis elle a été élue par mandat de réforme, et elle est maintenant le fer de lance de ce projet, L'Initiative islandaise pour la Modernisation des Médias. Et ils viennent de recevoir un financement pour en faire un projet de modernisation des médias internationnal, en prenant, à travers le monde, toutes les meilleures lois sur la liberté d'expression, la protection des dénonciateurs, la protection contre la diffamation, la protection des sources, en essayant de faire de l'Islande un paradis de la publication. Ce serait un endroit où les données seraient gratuites. Si l'on pense à la manière dont les gouvernements essaient d'accéder aux données des utilisateurs, ce qu'ils essaient de réaliser en Islande, c'est un refuge où cela serait possible. Dans le journalisme d'investigation, nous devons aussi commencer à penser global. Ce site s'appelle ID - Investigate Dashboard - et si vous voulez retrouver les actifs d'un dictateur, d'Hosni Mubarak disons, vous savez qu'il détourne des fonds de son pays quand il se sait en danger, pour enquêter à ce sujet, vous devez avoir accès à un maximum de bases de données d'inscriptions des entreprises, à travers le monde. Ceci est donc un site web qui tente de regrouper toutes ces bases de données en un seul endroit afin que vous puissiez y chercher sa famille, ses amis, le chef de son service de sécurité. Vous pouvez essayer d'y trouver sa méthode pour sortir ses actifs de son pays. Mais lorsqu'il s'agit des décisions qui nous affectent le plus, les décisions majeures, en matière de guerre par exemple, alors nous ne pouvons pas simplement déposer une demande d'accès à l'information. C'est vraiment compliqué. Nous sommes obligés d'avoir recours à des méthodes illicites pour obtenir des informations, les fuites. Lorsque le Guardian a enquêté sur la guerre en Afghanistan, ils ne pouvaient pas se présenter au Département de la défense et leur demander des informations. On ne leur aurait pas données. Elles sont donc arrivées par le biais de fuites, des milliers de dépêches écrites par des soldats américains au sujet de la guerre en Afghanistan, puis divulguées, et ensuite ils pouvaient enquêter. Une autre investigation majeure concerne la diplomatie mondiale. Encore une fois, elle repose sur des fuites, 251000 télégrammes diplomatiques américains, et j'ai été impliquée dans cette investigation parce que j'ai au accès à cette fuite par le biais d'une fuite d'un gars mécontent chez WikiLeaks et j'ai fini par travailler au Guardian. Alors, je suis bien placée pour vous expliquer ce que cela représente d'avoir accès à cette fuite. C'est incroyable. Ça m'a rappelé la scène dans le Magicien d'Oz. Vous voyez laquelle? Celle où le petit chien, Toto, court rejoindre le magicien, et il tire sur le rideau, et... "Ne regarde pas dans les le rideau. Ne regarde pas l'homme derrière le rideau." C'était exactement pareil, parce que ce qu'on a vu, c'était tous ces grands hommes d'états, ces politiciens pompeux, ils étaient exactement comme nous. Ils se critiquaient tous les uns les autres. Vraiment, assez médisants ces télégrammes. Je me suis dit que c'était plutôt important de pouvoir comprendre que ce sont des êtres humains au même titre que nous. Ils n'ont pas de pouvoirs spéciaux. Ils ne sont pas magiques. Ils ne sont pas nos parents. Au-delà de ça, le plus intéressant, c'est l'ampleur de la corruption endémique que j'ai constaté dans différents pays, et plus particulièrement au coeur du pouvoir, chez les agents publics qui détournaient l'argent des contribuables pour leur enrichissement personnel, et qui pouvaient le faire grâce aux secrets d'état. J'ai mentionné WikiLeaks car quoi de plus libre que de publier toutes ces documents? Et c'est ce que Julian Assange a fait. Il n'était pas satisfait de la manière dont les journeaux les publiaient, sans risques et légale. Il a tout dévoilé. Cela a eu pour conséquence d'exposer des personnes vulnérables en Afghanistan. Et de mettre une liste des militants pour la démocratie - ayant communiqué avec le gouvernement américain - entre les mains du dictateur biélorusse. Est-ce une liberté extrémiste? Je ne pense pas, car d'après moi, cela ne veut pas dire renoncer au pouvoir, aux obligations et à la responsabilité, c'est plutôt un partenariat avec le pouvoir. C'est un partage des obligations et des responsabilités. Le fait qu'il m'ait menacé de poursuite pour avoir glané une fuite de ses fuites montre, à mon avis, une incohérence assez notable sur le plan idéologique, pour être honnête. (Rires) Autre point. Le pouvoir est extrêmement seduisant et, selon, moi, il faut posséder deux grandes qualités quand vous passez à table, quand vous avez affaire au pouvoir, quand vous parlez de pouvoir, à cause de son pouvoir de séduction. Vous devez être sceptique et humble. Le scepticisme sert à toujours tout remettre en question. Je veux voir pourquoi...parce que vous le dites? Ce n'est pas suffisant. Je veux voir les preuves qui vont servir à justifier. L'humilité nous sert à être humain. Nous faisons tous des erreurs. Sans scepticisme et sans humilité, le passage de réformateur à desposte est très rapide. Il suffit de lire "La ferme des animaux" pour comprendre que le pouvoir corrompt. Quelle est donc la solution? Je pense qu'il faut appliquer le droit d'accès à l'information dans le cadre de l'état de droit. Actuellement, nos droits sont très peu protégés. Il existe une Loi sur les secrets officiels dans de nombreux pays, y compris la Grande-Bretagne. Nous avons cette Loi sur les secrets officiels sans qu'aucun critère d'intérêt public soit appliqué. Cela signifie que c'est un crime et que des gens sont punis, assez sévèrement dans de nombreux cas, pour avoir publié ou fourni des informations officielles. Ne serait-ce pas fantastique, et j'aimerais que vous y réfléchissiez, d'avoir une Loi sur la divulgation officielle selon laquelle les politiciens seraient punis en cas de dissimulation ou de suppression d'information d'intérêt public? Pour que....oui. Oui! Ma pose du pouvoir. (Applaudissements) (Rires) J'aimerais que nous oeuvrions dans ce sens. Ce ne sont pas que des mauvaises nouvelles. De réels progrés ont été réalisés, mais je pense que plus nous nous dirigeons droit dans le coeur du pouvoir, plus il devient opaque et fermé. L'autre semaine, j'ai entendu le commissaire de la police métropolitaine de Londres expliquer pourquoi la police avait besoin d'accéder à toutes nos communications - et de nous espionner sans contrôle judiciaire - et il a dit que c'était une question de vie ou de mort. Il a littéralement dit que c'était une question de vie ou de mort. Il n'y avait aucune preuve. Il n'a présenté aucune preuve de cela. C'était juste "Parce que je le dis. Vous devez me faire confiance. Croyez-en ma bonne foi." Alors vous m'excuserez, mais là nous sommes revenus à l'ère de l'Eglise pré-Lumières, et nous devons lutter. Il parlait d'une loi en Grande-Bretagne, la Loi des données de communications, une loi toute à fait scandaleuse. Aux Etats-Unis, il y a le CISPA - Cyber Intelligence Sharing and Protection Act. Ils se penchent même sur l'utilisation de drones pour la surveillance intérieure. L'Agence de Sécurité Nationale (NSA) est en train de construire le centre d'espionnage le plus géantissime du monde. Il est colossal, cinq fois plus grand que le Capitole des Etats-Unis, et ils vont y intercepter et analyser les communications, le trafic et les données personnelles afin d'essayer de découvrir le fauteur de trouble dans notre société. Bref, pour retourner à notre histoire, les parents ont paniqué. Ils ont fermé toutes les portes à clé. Ils ont rempli la maison de caméras de surveillance CCTV. Ils nous espionnent tous. Ils ont creusé une cave, et ils ont construit un centre d'espionnage pour cerner, à l'aide d'algorithmes, lesquels d'entre nous sont importuns, et si l'un de nous s'en plaint, il est arrêté pour terrorisme. Conte de fées ou cauchemar? Certains contes de fées ont un dénouement heureux. D'autres pas. Je pense que nous avons tous lu les contes de Grimm, qui sont plutôt noirs. Mais le monde n'est pas un conte de fées, il est peut-être plus barbare que nous ne voulons l'admettre. De même, il est peut-être meilleur que ce qu'on nous a porté à croire. Dans tous les cas, nous devons essayer de le voir tel qu'il est, avec ses problèmes, car c'est seulement en l'examinant avec ses problèmes que nous pourrons les résoudre et ensemble dans ce monde, vivre heureux à tout jamais. (Rires) Merci beaucoup. (Applaudissements) Merci. (Applaudissements)